Rosa Parks Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Rosa Parks Papers 1866-2006 (bulk 1955-2000)
MSS85943
Parks, Rosa, 1913-2005
7,500 items
40 containers plus 17 oversize and 1 artifact container
50 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Civil rights activist. Correspondence; family papers; writings; notes; statements; programs; medals, resolutions, and other honors; financial, employment, health, and estate records; drawings; photographs; address books; appointment calendars; memorabilia; magazine and newspaper clippings; books; and other printed matter documenting her personal life and civil rights activism.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Arberry family.; Carr, Johnnie Rebecca, 1911-2008.; Clark, Septima Poinsette, 1898-1987.; Conyers, John, Jr., 1929-; Durr, Virginia Foster.; Edwards family.; Gray, Fred D., 1930-; Haley, Alex.; Killens, John Oliver, 1916-1987.; King, Coretta Scott, 1927-2006.; King, Martin Luther, Jr., 1929-1968--Interviews.; King, Martin Luther, Jr., 1929-1968.; McCauley family.; McCauley, Leona Edwards, 1888-1979--Correspondence.; McCauley, Sylvester James, 1915-1977--Correspondence.; Mitford, Jessica, 1917-1996.; Moore, Audley, 1898-1997.; Morris, Edita, 1902-1988--Correspondence.; Nixon, Edgar Daniel--Interviews.; Parks family.; Parks, Raymond A. (Raymond Arthur), 1903-1977--Correspondence.; Parks, Rosa, 1913-2005--Interviews.; Parks, Rosa, 1913-2005--Medals.; Parks, Rosa, 1913-2005.; Percival family.; Rustin, Bayard, 1912-1987.; Stokes, Olivia Pearl, 1916-; Terkel, Studs, 1912-2008.; Thomas, Clarence, 1948-; Williams, Aubrey Willis, 1890-1965.; Williams, Aubrey Willis, 1890-1965. Aubrey Willis Williams oral history interviews and writings.
Organizations
Hampton Institute.; Highlander Folk School (Monteagle, Tenn.); March on Washington for Jobs and Freedom (1963: Washington, D.C.); Martin Luther King, Jr. Center for Nonviolent Social Change.; Mississippi Freedom Project.; National Association for the Advancement of Colored People.; Prayer Pilgrimage for Freedom (1957: Washington, D.C.); Rosa and Raymond Parks Institute for Self Development.; Southern Christian Leadership Conference.; St. Matthew African Methodist Episcopal Church (Detroit, Mich.)
Subjects
African American churches.; African American youth.; African Americans--Civil rights.; African Americans--Religion.; African Americans--Segregation.; African Americans--Social conditions.; African Americans--Societies, etc.; African Americans.; Boycotts--Alabama.; Civil rights demonstrations--Alabama.; Civil rights demonstrations--United States.; Civil rights movements--United States.; Civil rights--United States.; Civil rights.; Congressional Award.; Montgomery Bus Boycott, Montgomery, Ala., 1955-1956.; Poor People's Campaign.; Presidential Medal of Freedom.; Race discrimination--Southern States.; Race discrimination--United States.; Segregation--Southern States.; Segregation--United States.; World War, 1939-1945--Participation, African American.
Places
Michigan--Religion.; Michigan--Social life and customs.; Southern States--Race relations.; Southern States--Social conditions.; United States--Race relations.; United States--Social conditions.; United States--Social policy.
Titles
Rosa Parks Papers at the Library of Congress
Occupations
Civil rights activists.
Provenance
The papers of Rosa Parks, civil rights activist, were placed on deposit at the Library of Congress by the Howard G. Buffett Foundation in 2014, and converted to a gift in 2016.
Transfers
Items have been transferred from the Manuscript Division to other custodial divisions of the Library. Some photographs have been transferred to the Prints and Photographs Division. Sound recordings have been transferred to the Motion Picture, Broadcasting, and Recorded Sound Division. All transfers are identified in these divisions as part of the Rosa Parks Papers.
Other Repositories
Other papers of Rosa Parks can be found at the Walter P. Reuther Library, Wayne State University, Detroit, Michigan.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Rosa Parks are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Online Content
The papers of Rosa Parks are available on the Library of Congress Web site at http://hdl.loc.gov/loc.mss/collmss.ms000037.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1913, Feb. 4 Born, Tuskegee, Ala.
1914 Moved to Pine Level, Ala.
1924 1929 Attended the Montgomery Industrial School, Montgomery, Ala.
1932 Married Raymond A. Parks (died 1977)
1933 Received high school degree
1943 Selected as secretary, NAACP Montgomery, Ala., branch
1949 Became an advisor to the Youth Council of the NAACP Montgomery, Ala., branch
1955 Attended a workshop at the Highlander Folk School, Monteagle, Tenn., in August Arrested on December 1 and charged with violating Montgomery, Ala., segregation laws by refusing to give up her bus seat to a white passenger Participated in organizing a boycott of the Montgomery bus system
1956 Lost her job in January as an assistant tailor at the Montgomery Fair department store, Montgomery, Ala. Arrested along with other boycott organizers for violating anti-boycott laws
1957 Moved to Detroit, Mich. Participated in the Prayer Pilgrimage for Freedom
1957 1958 Hostess, Holly Tree Inn, Hampton Institute, Hampton, Va.
1958 Returned to Detroit, Mich.
1963 Participated in the March on Washington for Jobs and Freedom
1965 Participated in the Selma-to-Montgomery March
1965 1988 Worked in Congressman John Conyers's district office in Detroit, Mich.
1979 Awarded the NAACP Spingarn Medal
1987 Founded the Rosa and Raymond Parks Institute for Self Development
1992 Published with Jim Haskins Rosa Parks: My Story. New York: Dial Books
1994 Published with Gregory J. Reed Quiet Strength: The Faith, the Hope, the Heart of a Woman Who Changed a Nation. Grand Rapids, Mich.: Zondervan Publishing House
1996 Awarded the Presidential Medal of Freedom Published with Gregory J. Reed Dear Mrs. Parks: A Dialogue with Today's Youth. New York: Lee and Low Books
1999 Awarded the Congressional Gold Medal
2005, Oct. 24 Died, Detroit, Mich.; lay in honor in the United States Capitol Rotunda
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Rosa Louise Parks (1913-2005) span the years 1866-2006, with the bulk of the material dating from 1955 to 2000. The collection documents many aspects of Parks's private life and public activism on behalf of civil rights for African Americans. An array of personal papers contains family papers, correspondence, writings, notes, statements, event programs and invitations, tributes, medals, photographs, printed matter, books owned by her, and a variety of employment, financial, health, and residential records that reveal much about the material conditions of her life. Events surrounding her arrest in 1955 for violating Montgomery, Alabama, segregation laws by refusing to give up her seat to a white passenger, as well as the subsequent Montgomery Bus Boycott, are described in many of her writings, notes, and correspondence from 1955 to 1956. The collection is arranged in eleven series: Family Papers; General Correspondence; Subject File; Writings, Notes, and Statements; Events; Resolutions and Other Honors; Miscellany; Printed Matter; Books Owned by Parks; Medals; and Oversize.
The Family Papers open a window into some of Rosa Parks's most important relationships. The series contains her correspondence with family members, most notably her husband Raymond A. Parks, her mother Leona McCauley, and her brother Sylvester McCauley. Correspondence with her husband and mother contains the largest number of letters written by her in the collection. Her letters to Raymond Parks date between 1957 and 1958 when she was living and working at the Hampton Institute in Virginia and he was living in Detroit. Written in the aftermath of the bus boycott, the letters reveal the personal toll those events took on both of them and the emotional hardship of their separation. Rosa Parks's back-and-forth correspondence with her mother Leona McCauley is more voluminous and spans several decades, largely from the late 1940s to McCauley's death in 1979. The letters were written during periods when they were apart from one another, most significantly between 1956 and 1958 during Rosa Parks's speaking tours and employment at the Hampton Institute. James McCauley, Parks's father, was not a consistent part of her life, a circumstance he reflects on in a letter written to her in 1950. Letters by Sylvester McCauley largely concern his efforts to convince his sister to move to Detroit. Correspondence with extended family consists of letters from nieces, nephews, aunts, cousins, and other family members. Also included in the series are other family papers that shed further light on the lives of Parks's husband, mother, father, and brother. Raymond A. Parks's papers include several letters from friends and acquaintances, as well as employment records, barber licenses, photographs, certificates, Masonic dues books, and receipts, including one from their move to Detroit in 1957. Among Leona McCauley's papers is an exchange of letters in 1956 with writer and political activist Edita Morris. Some of Sylvester McCauley's papers relate to his military service in World War II.
The General Correspondence series is arranged in four files: an alphabetical file, a chronological file, greeting cards, and letters and drawings from children. The alphabetical file contains letters from prominent individuals and those who played a significant role in Parks's life. Among them are Johnnie Rebecca Carr, a prominent member of Montgomery's civil rights movement; Septima Poinsette Clark of the Highlander Folk School; Virginia Foster Durr, a white civil rights advocate living in Montgomery; and Fred D. Gray who represented Parks after her arrests in 1955 and 1956. Also included is a note from civil rights leader Audley Moore, better known as Queen Mother Moore. A postcard written by Martin Luther King, Jr., while traveling in Europe in 1957 was kept by Parks in a keepsake portfolio that is currently filed in the Miscellany series. The postcard was transferred to the alphabetical correspondence file during processing. Letters signed "Galatas" are from a childhood friend living in Harrisburg, Pennsylvania. The alphabetical file features several letters written by Parks in 1956-1957, including one to "Anne," possibly Anne Braden, and another to Jessica Mitford, both of which describe events during the Montgomery Bus Boycott.
A chronological file of largely incoming correspondence spans the years 1948-2006, but is more heavily weighted toward the last decades of Parks's life. The earliest correspondence in the 1940s and 1950s contains invitations to weddings and graduations, but also letters from friends and others, some of which make reference to civil rights issues. Later correspondence is composed principally of letters from organizations, event planners, some friends and acquaintances, and private individuals who wrote to express their admiration for her. Many of these letters contain requests for her to appear at events, to grant permission to quote from her interviews and writings, and to comment on scripts and other writings sent to her by the authors. A large file of greeting cards contains well wishes sent by friends and the public on her birthday, holidays, and during her periodic illnesses. Letters from school children, often illustrated, convey endearing, unselfconscious expressions of admiration.
The Subject File focuses more narrowly on Parks's affiliation with several organizations and institutions, her participation in major civil rights events, and various efforts to honor her. Material on her institutional memberships ranges from the Masonic Order of Eastern Star to St. Matthew Church in Detroit. Many of the programs from her home church contain her notes and annotations. Included among the material from the Highlander Folk School is a 1963 flyer condemning it as "a communist training school" and reprinting an often-reproduced photograph of Parks, Martin Luther King, Jr., and others at the school's twenty-fifth anniversary in 1957. Files are also featured from leading civil rights organizations including the Martin Luther King, Jr. Center for Nonviolent Social Change, the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP), and the Southern Christian Leadership Conference. Notable among the major civil rights events documented in the file is the Montgomery Bus Boycott. Most of this material dates from the boycott itself and includes draft instructions to car-pool drivers and passengers written in Parks's hand and a Montgomery Fair department store date book for 1955 that Parks used as a notebook during 1956. In it are lists of names, including drivers during the boycott, as well as notes and reflections during that critical year. These items suggest the active role she played in helping to organize the boycott. Other material on the boycott includes a series of typescripts of writings and interviews by Aubrey Willis Williams, most of which are annotated and corrected by Parks. Interview transcripts consist of those between Williams and Martin Luther King, Jr., Edgar Daniel Nixon, and Parks. Articles and a series of chronologies, most of which are attributed to Williams and annotated by Parks, concern Parks's arrest, the subsequent bus boycott, and race relations in the South in general. Material relating to the Prayer Pilgrimage for Freedom in 1957 includes advice to her from Bayard Rustin. Ephemera documents her participation in other key events and includes a copy of the first organizing manual for the March on Washington in 1963 and her name tag and identity card from the Mississippi Freedom Summer Project in 1964 and the Poor People's Campaign in 1968. Also explored in the Subject File are efforts to honor Parks, among them the creation of two national committees, the renaming of a Detroit street in her honor, the establishment of a scholarship named for her, and the awarding of the Presidential Medal of Freedom in 1996 and Congressional Gold Medal in 1999. A small file stemming from her work in Congressman John Conyers's Detroit office and files from the Rosa and Raymond Parks Institute for Self Development, an organization founded by her to promote youth development and civil rights education, round out the series.
Rosa Parks's Writings, Notes, and Statements are organized as a separate series and span several decades from her arrest on December 1, 1955, to her final years at the end of the twentieth century. The series includes galleys and other items from three co-authored books by her; drafts of writings from around 1956-1958; prayers and spiritual reflections; statements honoring John Conyers and opposing the appointment of Clarence Thomas to the Supreme Court; and notes that range from note-taking at meetings to random personal reflections to mundane jottings. A notebook, probably dated 1956, records in part her travels to California where she had numerous speaking engagements and attended the NAACP annual convention in San Francisco. Perhaps most notable among her writings are two folders of handwritten, draft accounts of her arrest, the subsequent bus boycott, and the dynamics of race relations in the South. Although undated, some of these drafts are written on the back of 1956 letters, envelopes, and a program. It is likely that many of them were written that year, possibly for speeches given by Parks. Some may have been written between 1957 and1958 when Parks was living and working at the Hampton Institute. Also of note are drafts of autobiographical writings in which Parks explored the impact of racism and discrimination on her own life. It is uncertain why she wrote these drafts. Some may have been written as notes for interviews or speeches, or she may have considered writing her memoirs in either article or book form.
Many of Parks's speaking engagements, the honors she received, and events she attended are documented in an Events series that contains programs, invitations, flyers, and other publicity material. The file is arranged in two sections: events featuring or honoring Parks and a general file for events that she most likely attended even though her name does not appear in the programs. Items from events featuring or honoring Parks trace the evolving way Parks was remembered and honored by the American public. Some of the earliest events were organized as fund-raising benefits to assist the Parks family as it struggled financially in the aftermath of her arrest. Later events focused more exclusively on celebrating her as an iconic national hero and the "mother of the civil rights movement." The programs in the general file are useful in documenting the organizations, people, and movements she supported by her mere attendance. The collection also includes numerous resolutions, tributes, honorary degrees, and other honors awarded to Parks. These are arranged as a separate series and are housed among the collection's Oversize material.
A Miscellany series documents many day-to-day and material aspects of Rosa Parks's life including her employment, financial status, health, memberships, donations, household furnishings, residences, and circle of friends, family, associates, and contacts. Employment files largely consist of pay stubs and vouchers, including those from the Montgomery Fair department store where Parks was employed as an assistant tailor at the time of her arrest. Income tax records track the financial status of the Parkses from 1943 to 1987 and expose the couple's prolonged financial struggle following Rosa Parks's arrest in 1955. Other records including insurance and banking records and receipts for household goods and rent provide further insight into their financial conditions and coping strategies. Rosa Parks's web of personal connections is partially documented through address books, invitation lists, and telephone messages. Telephone messages dated 1974-1975 in particular provide a glimpse into the casework handled by Parks and other staff in Congressman John Conyers's Detroit office.
The Printed Matter series contains material about Parks and collected by her. Collected material focuses on such topics as civil rights, Martin Luther King, Jr., and religion. It also includes commemorative stamps sent to her by others and magazines and newspapers she presumably read and saved. Magazines and newspapers with articles about Parks or briefly mentioning her are arranged separately within the printed matter. The collection also contains books owned by Parks. Some of the earliest publications were owned by family members whose names are written in the books. Prominent among the family-owned books is a Bible recording births, deaths, and marriages of members of the Percival, Arberry, and Edwards families. Copies of the family register pages have also been made available in the Family Papers series. Some of the later books contain inscriptions to Parks by Fred D. Gray, Alex Haley, John Oliver Killens, Coretta Scott King, Olivia Pearl Stokes, and Studs Terkel, among others.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged in eleven series:
Family Papers, 1900-2005
General Correspondence, 1928-2006
Subject File, 1937-2005
Writings, Notes, and Statements, 1956-1998
Events, 1951-2005
Resolutions and Other Honors, 1967-2006
Miscellany, 1934-2005
Printed Matter, 1947-2005
Books Owned by Parks, 1866-2001
Medals, 1996-1999
Oversize, 1900-2006
Container List
- Family Papers, 1900-2005 (Box 1-3)
  Correspondence, certificates, memorials, notes, financial records, employment records, insurance documents, medical records, photographs, news clippings, and other material pertaining to the family of Rosa Parks.
  Arranged in two parts: letters to and from Rosa Parks, and other family papers. Letters to and from Parks are arranged alphabetically by name of immediate family member, with letters from extended family grouped together in a chronological arrangement. Other family papers contain material belonging to and documenting the lives of Parks's husband, mother, brother, and father. They are arranged alphabetically by name of family member and alphabetically thereunder by topic or type of material.
  - Letters to and from Rosa Parks (Box 1)
    - Extended family
      - 1948-1964
      - 1973-1976
      - 1977-1981
      - 1982-1985
      - 1986-1989
      - 1990-1993
      - 1994-1997
      - 1998-2005
      - Undated See also Oversize
    - McCauley, James (father), 1950 (Box 2)
    - McCauley, Leona (mother)
      - 1936, 1946
      - 1948-1953
      - 1956
      - 1957
      - 1958
      - 1961-1976
      - 1977-1979
      - Undated
    - McCauley, Sylvester (brother)
      - 1944-1947
      - 1951-1957
    - Parks, Raymond A. (husband)
      - 1957
      - 1958
        - 1958, Jan.-Mar.
        - 1958, Apr.-Oct.
  - Other family papers
    - Copies of family register pages in family Bible, circa 1900-1941 See also Containers 34 and OV 17, Holy Bible, C. H. Robinson
    - Edwards, Bessie D., memorial and clipping on her death, 1905
    - Lists of family members, 1988, undated
    - McCauley, James (father), 1961, undated
    - McCauley, Leona (mother)
      - Correspondence with others
        - 1956, 1969-1975
        - 1976-1979, undated
      - Miscellany, 1954, 1961-1963, 1974-1980, undated See also Oversize
    - McCauley, Sylvester (brother) (Box 3)
      - Correspondence with others, 1944-1945, 1951, 1957
      - Miscellany, 1915, 1943-1949, 1961
    - Parks, Raymond A. (husband)
      - Ancient Egyptian Arabic Order Nobles of the Mystic Shrine of North and South America and Its Jurisdiction, 1945-1946
      - Barber's licenses and a note about barber's examination, 1957-1960, 1968
      - Correspondence with others, 1946, 1952-1959
      - Death of, 1977
      - Employment, 1950-1959
      - Income tax records See Container 24, same heading
      - Insurance
        - 1942-1951
        - 1944-1947, 1956
      - International Railway Correspondence Institute, diploma, 1928
      - Miscellany, circa 1955, 1965, 1977
      - Notebook, undated
      - Photographs, circa 1923, 1947, 1970s
      - Receipts
        - Barber supplies, 1951, 1964-1966
        - Medical, 1956-1957, 1965-1977
        - Miscellaneous, 1940-1947, 1956-1959, 1974
        - Move to Detroit, Mich., 1957
    - Percival family, two news clippings, undated
- General Correspondence, 1928-2006 (Box 3-13)
  Correspondence, greeting cards, and children's drawings.
  Arranged in four parts. An alphabetical file containing correspondence from individuals prominent in Parks's life is arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent. A chronological file of largely incoming letters, a file of greeting cards, and letters and drawings from children are each arranged chronologically.
  - Alphabetical file (Box 3)
    - "Anne," draft letter by Parks possibly to Anne Braden, 1956
    - Bond, James and Julian, 1986
    - Bond, Marion O., undated
    - Bush, George W., Voting Rights Act Reauthorization and Amendments Act of 2006, 2006
    - Carr, Johnnie Rebecca, 1962, 1990
    - Clark, Septima Poinsette, 1961, 1972
    - Clinton, Bill, 1993-2000
    - Conyers, John, 1965, 1971, 1982-1987, undated
    - Durr, Virginia Foster, 1954-1962, 1973-1981, 1990, undated
    - Fonda, Jane, and Tom Hayden, holiday greeting, 1983
    - "Galatas," 1928-1932
    - Gore, Al, 1996 (Box 4)
    - Gray, Fred D., 1975-1977 See also Container 31, Daniels, Pearl Gray